Guide to the Marc Allégret Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marc Allegrét papers
1900-1972
1920-1956
GEN MSS 651
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.51
(16 boxes)
The Marc Allégret Papers document Allégret 's career as a filmmaker and his association with author André Gide. Allegrét's working files include screenplays, shooting scripts, correspondence, background and research materials, production notes and documents, cut film, photographs, and printed ephemera. There are screenplays or shooting scripts for over a dozen feature-length films and larger, mixed files for the documentaries Voyage au Congo (1927), Occultisme et magie (1951), and Avec André Gide (1952). The files for Voyage au Congo also document Allegrét's travels with Gide through French equatorial Africa in the mid 1920s. Works by Others include writings by Gide and screenplays and shooting scripts by Allégret's collaborators. Works by Gide include corrected drafts and proofs for several titles dating from the 1920s, such as Corydon (1924) and Retour du Tchad (1927). Correspondence consists of letters to Allégret from Françoise Giroud, Roger Martin du Gard, and Roger Vadim, and third party correspondence between André Gide, Madeleine Louise Mathilde Gide, Elie Allégret, Roger Martin du Gard, producer Pierre Braunberger, and others.
Allégret, Marc, 1900-1973
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marc Allégret Papers was aquired through purchase from Librarie Benoit Forgeot on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Cut film contained in boxes 2-3 and 10 is restricted and may only be seen with permission of the appropriate curator.
Marc Allégret (1900-1973)
Marc Allégret, a French screenwriter and filmmaker, was born in Basel, Switzerland and trained as a lawyer. After travelling in French equatorial Africa in the mid 1920s with André Gide, Allégret chose to pursue a career in the film industry. He directed his first feature-length film, Mam'zelle Nitouche, in 1931 and went on to write numerous scripts and direct more than fifty films. He was the elder brother of Yves Allégret, also a filmmaker. Additional information is available in standard print and online biographical resources.
The following chronology provides dates for key events and film projects for which there are files in the collection:
1900 December 22 born in Basel, Switzerland
1925-1926 travel with André Gide in French equatorial Africa
1927 Voyage au Congo
1934 Zouzou
1934 L'Hôtel du libre échange
1937 Gribouille
1938 Orage
1942 L'Arlésienne
1942 La belle aventure
1944 Les petites du quai aux fleurs
1945 Félicie Nanteuil
1946 Lunegarde
1946 Pétrus
1951 Occultisme et magie
1952 Avec André Gide
1953 Julietta
1955 L'Amant de lady Chatterley
1970 Le bal du comte d'Orgel
1973 November 3 dies in Versailles, France
Scope and Contents
The Marc Allégret papers feature material relating to films shot or directed by Allégret and to his association with André Gide. Allégret's working files include screenplays, shooting scripts, correspondence, background and research materials, production notes and documents, cut film, photographs, and printed ephemera dating from his earliest cinematic effort, the documentary Voyage au Congo (1927), to his last feature-length film, Le bal du comte d'Orgel (1970). Allégret became acquainted with Gide through his father's friendship and his travels with Gide into Africa in the mid 1920s are richly documented in the production files, which include correspondence, manuscript notes, photographs, and ephemera, for Voyage au Congo. Other materials relating more or less directly to Gide include the production files for the late documentary Avec André Gide (1952), corrected drafts and proofs for several titles by Gide from the 1920s, and third-party correspondence. Works by Others also include screenplays and shooting scripts by some of Allégret's collaborators. General correspondence consists of letters to Marc Allégret from Françoise Giroud, Roger Martin du Gard, and Roger Vadim, with over seventy pieces of correspondence from Martin du Gard. Third Party correspondence features approximately thirty pieces of correspondence between Marc Allégret's father, Elie Allégret, and André Gide, and include letters from Gide's wife Madeleine, Roger Martin du Gard, and producer Pierre Braunberger. Chiefly in French, with some materials in German and English.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Works by Marc Allégret, 1907-1969. II. Works by Others, 1919-1971. III. Correspondence, 1900-1972.
Cinematography; Motion picture producers and directors; Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Motion pictures -- France; Africa, French-speaking Equatorial -- Description and travel; Cameroon -- Description and travel; Film scripts; Photographic prints; Printed ephemera; Motion picture producers and directors; Allégret, E. (Elie); Allégret, Marc, 1900-1973; Braunberger, Pierre, 1905-1990; Gide, André, 1869-1951; Gide, Madeleine Louise Mathilde, approximately 1867-1938; Giroud, Françoise, 1916-2003; Martin Du Gard, Roger, 1881-1958; Vadim, Roger, 1928-2000
- Works by Marc Allégret, 1907-1969; Series I; 4.17; (11 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by film title.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Works by Marc Allégret, housed in boxes 1-11, consists of material relating to films shot or directed by Allégret throughout his career as a filmmaker. Materials include screenplays, shooting scripts, correspondence, background and research materials, production notes and documents, cut film, photographs, and printed ephemera. There are screenplays or shooting scripts for over a dozen feature-length films and larger, mixed files for three documentaries, Voyage au Congo (1927), Occultisme et magie (1951), and Avec André Gide (1952).
  The files for Voyage au Congo, including correspondence, manuscript material, photographs, and printed ephemera, document Allegrét's travels with André Gide through French equatorial Africa in the mid 1920s--Gide's journals were also published shortly after their return as Voyage au Congo (1927) and Retour du Tchad (1928). Material identified in the list below as "Notes and notebooks" preserves folders of letters, background material, itineraries, lists of supplies, financial records, journal entries, ethnographic observations, language aids, and other papers. Correspondence relating chiefly to distribution of the documentary, as well as to publication of photographs, can be found in the "Correspondence" folders, which date from 1927 to 1930, while correspondence relating to travel can be found scattered throughout the "Notes and notebooks". Correspondents include Kodak founder George Eastman, to whom there is a draft of a letter, in English, soliticting camera equipment for "artistic and scientific research," and colleagues of Allégret's father, Elie, at the Sociéte des mission évangéliques de Paris.
  The Voyage au Congo materials in Series I complement the research materials, drafts, and proofs relating to Gide's travel writings in Series II. Together these two groups of material document travel through areas now known as the Republic of the Congo, the Central African Republic, Chad, and Cameroon, and aspects of life in parts of these countries, including colonial attitudes and relationships.
  Allégret's documentary on André Gide, released shortly after Gide's death in 1951, combines still photographs, documentary and newsreel footage, and interviews. Files for the film include correspondence, manuscript material, and cut film. The manuscript material (also identified in the list as "Notes") preserves folders of correspondence, lists of photographs and documents used in the film, drafts of interviews and commentary, financial records, and other papers relating to the production and distribution of the film. Correspondents include: Gaston Criel, Henri Langlois of the Cinémathèque française, Jean Duché, Jean Schlumberger, René Gustave Nobécourt, Jean-Louis Barrault, Roger Martin du Gard, Justin O'Brien, Pierre Herbart, Philippe Halsman, Yvonne Davet, Georges Sirot, and many others; included are letters to and from Allégret's assistant Pierre Boursaus.
  The files for Occultisme et magie, including correspondence, printed ephemera, photographs, and manuscript material, feature drafts of interviews, essays, and notes on the following topics: astrology, black magic, occultism and science, parapsychology, alchemy, hypnotism, faith and medicine healers, spiritualism, yoga, and fakirs. There is material by or relating to Robert Amadou, Jean Piverd, Jean Auscher, Scarha-Bey, Jean Thévenot, and others.
  Many of Allégret's feature films, such as L'Amant de Lady Chatterly and Le Bal du Comte d'Orgel, were adapted from literary works, and the dialogue and/or screenplays were either written by others or in collaboration with Allégret. Contributors include Marcel Achard, Françoise Giroud, H. G. Lustig, Charles de Peyret-Chappuis, and Carlo Rim. French composer Georges Auric also wrote scores for a number of Allégret's films, and music to a theatrical adaptation of Volpone by Jules Romains can be found in Series II.
  Cut film is stored in cold storage.
  - L'amant de Lady Chatterley
    - Screenplay, typescript, 1954 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - L'arlésienne
    - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Shooting script, typescript, corrected, [ca. 1941] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Avec André Gide
    - Correspondence, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Cut film, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 8-19)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Cut film, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 20-25)
    - Notes, 1931-1952, undated (Box 4, Folder 26-44)
      Includes correspondence
  - Le bal du comte d'Orgel
    - Clippings, undated
    - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Shooting scripts, typescript, 1969, undated (Box 5, Folder 46-47)
  - La belle aventure
    - Notes, 1942 September 4 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Shooting script, annotated, [1942?] (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Félicie Nanteuil
    - Screenplay, holograph fragments, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Shooting script, typescript, [ca. 1945] (Box 6, Folder 51-53)
  - Gribouille
    - Screenplay, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - L'hôtel du libre échange
    - Shooting script, typescript, corrected, [ca. 1934] (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Julietta
    - Screenplay, typescript, 1953 April 17 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Shooting script, typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Lunegarde
    - Correspondence, 1941, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Documents, undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Occultisme et magie
    - Documents, 1950-1953, undated (Box 7, Folder 61-81)
    - Documents, 1950-1953, undated (Box 8, Folder 82-83)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Printed ephemera, 1950-1953, undated (Box 8, Folder 85-86)
  - Orage
    - Notes, 1937, undated (Box 8, Folder 87-88)
    - Screenplay, typescript, including clippings of Émile Zola's La Bete humaine, undated (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Les petites du quai aux fleurs
    - Shooting script, typescript, 1943 June (Box 8, Folder 90-92)
  - Pétrus
    - Screenplay, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Shooting script, typescript, [ca. 1945] (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Voyage au Congo
    - Correspondence, 1927-1930, undated (Box 9, Folder 95-96)
    - Notes and notebooks, 1907-1927 (Box 9, Folder 97-106)
    - Notes and notebooks, 1925-1926, undated (Box 10, Folder 107-114)
      Includes correspondence and cut film
    - Photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Printed ephemera, 1924-1928, undated (Box 10, Folder 116-117)
  - Zouzou
    - Shooting script, typescript, corrected, [ca. 1934] (Box 10, Folder 118-122)
    - Shooting script, typescript, corrected, [ca. 1934] (Box 11, Folder 123-124)
    - Printed ephemera, undated
- Works by Others, 1919-1971; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically first by name of author, then by title.
  Series II, Works by Others, housed in boxes 12-14, consists of two main groups of materials, writings by André Gide and screenplays and shooting scripts by some of Allégret's cinematic collaborators. The Gide materials feature corrected proofs, as well as a couple drafts, for several titles dating between 1919 and 1927. There are proofs, for example, for Gide's travel journals, Voyage au Congo (1927) and Retour du Tchad (1928), which are complemented by the extensive notes and materials relating to Allégret's documentary project in Series I, as well as for La symphonie pastorale and Corydon. In addition, there are drafts for Retour du Tchad and an essay, entitled "Les villages des tribus Massas", based on his travels.
  The screenplays and shooting scripts listed in Series II are for works that were not realized, such as Prévert's "Comme la plume au vent", or filmed by another director, such as Drôle de drame and Les visiteurs du soir, both of which were directed by Marcel Carné. Contributors include Françoise Giroud, Pierre Larouche, Roger Martin du Gard, Jacques Prévert, Jules Romaine, and Roger Vadim.
  - Gide, André
    - Corydon
      - Page proof, corrected, [1924?] (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - "La porte étroite"
      - Printed publicity for 1920 adaptation, 1920 February 11 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Retour du Tchad
      - Research materials, 1920-1927, undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, [1927] (Box 12, Folder 128)
      - Proofs, corrected, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 129-131)
    - La symphonie pastoral
      - Proofs, corrected, [ca. 1919] (Box 12, Folder 132-133)
    - Typhon
      - Page proofs, corrected, of translation of work by Joseph Conrad, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - "Les villages des tribus Massas"
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 12, Folder 135)
      - Proof, corrected, 1927 February 18 (Box 12, Folder 136)
    - Voyage au Congo
      - Page proofs, corrected, 1927 March (Box 13, Folder 137-139)
  - Giroud, Françoise
    - "Les memoires de poisson rouge"
      - Screenplays, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 140-141)
  - Laroche, Pierre
  - Martin du Gard, Roger
    - "Frere et soeur"
      - Screenplay, typescript, [ca. 1930] (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - "Paysan"
      - Screenplay, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - "Rapport sur la situation du cinema français..."
      - Drafts, 1930, undated (Box 13, Folder 144)
        Includes correspondence and printed materials
  - Prévert, Jacques
    - "Comme la plume au vent"
      - Screenplay, typescript, [1941] (Box 13, Folder 145-146)
    - Drôle de drame
      - Shooting script, typescript, [ca. 1937] (Box 14, Folder 147-148)
    - Les visiteurs du soir
      - Shooting script, typescript, [ca. 1942] (Box 14, Folder 149)
  - Romains, Jules
    - Volpone
      - Printed version, corrected and annotated, 1929, undated (Box 14, Folder 150)
      - Score by Georges Auric, undated (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - Vadim, Roger
    - "Petit roman joli"
      - Novella, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 14, Folder 152)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1947-1971, undated (Box 14, Folder 153-154)
      Includes drafts of screenplays, notes, financial records, and printed ephemera
- Correspondence, 1900-1972; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Organized into two subseries for General Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
  General correspondence consists of letters to Marc Allégret from Françoise Giroud, Roger Martin du Gard, and Roger Vadim, with over 70 pieces of correspondence from Martin du Gard. Third Party correspondence features approximately 30 pieces of correspondence between Marc Allégret's father, Elie Allégret, and André Gide, and include letters from Gide's wife Madeleine, Roger Martin du Gard, and producer Pierre Bruanberger.
  Correspondence can also be found in the production files for works by Allégret in Series I.
  - General Correspondence
    - Giroud, Françoise, 1951-1956, undated (Box 15, Folder 155)
    - Martin du Gard, Roger, 1925-1955, undated (Box 15, Folder 156-158)
    - Vadim, Roger, 1947-1972, undated (Box 15, Folder 159)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - Allégret, Elie to André Gide, 1900-1926 (Box 15, Folder 160-161)
    - Braunberger, Pierre to Roger Vadim, 1948 July 28 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - Gide, André to Elie Allégret, 1900-1940 (Box 15, Folder 163-164)
    - Gide, André to [Pierre Feuillere?], 1942 October 2 (Box 15, Folder 165)
    - Gide, André to Lucien Vogel, 1944, undated (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - Gide, André to Nadine Vogel, 1937-1943, undated (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - Gide, Madeleine to Elie Allégret, 1900 (Box 15, Folder 168)
    - Martin du Gard, Roger to Nadine Allégret, 1942-1944 (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - Others to Roger Vadim, 1949-1950, undated (Box 15, Folder 170)
- Oversize, 1.67; (1 box)
  Oversize material, housed in box 16, is arranged in folder order.
  - Clipping for Le bal du Comte d'Orgel (In Series I), undated (Box 16, Folder 171)
  - Clippings for Occultisme et magie (In Series I), 1950, undated (Box 16, Folder 172)
  - Printed ephemera for Voyage au Congo (In Series I), 1927-1928, undated (Box 16, Folder 173-175)
  - Printed ephemera for Zouzou (In Series I), undated (Box 16, Folder 176)
  - Research material for Retour du Tchad (In Series II), 1925 September (Box 16, Folder 177)
  - Clipping on Roger Vadim (In Series II), 1971 September 7 (Box 16, Folder 178)
  - Letter from Roger Vadim to Marc Allégret (In Series III), undated (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Clipping from letter to Elie Allégret from André Gide (In Series III), undated (Box 16, Folder 180)